Well we all know the World Wide Web
حسنا، كلنا يعرف أن الشبكة العنكبوتية العالمية
has absolutely transformed publishing, broadcasting,
غيرت كثيرا النشر والبث
commerce and social connectivity,
والتجارة والاتصال الاجتماعي
but where did it all come from?
لكن من أين أتى كل هذا؟
And I'll quote three people:
وسوف اقتبس عن ثلاثة أشخاص:
Vannevar Bush, Doug Engelbart and Tim Berners-Lee.
"فانيفار بوش" و "دوغ إنغيلبارت" و "تيم بيرنرز-لي"
So let's just run through these guys.
إذن لنمرّ على هؤلاء الأشخاص.
This is Vannevar Bush.
هذا هو فانيفار بوش.
Vannevar Bush was the U.S. government's chief scientific adviser during the war.
كان فانيفار بوش أكبر مستشار علمي للحكومة الأمريكية خلال الحرب العالمية الثانية.
And in 1945,
وفي 1945،
he published an article in a magazine called Atlantic Monthly.
نشر مقالا في مجلة تُدعى أتلانتيك مانثلي.
And the article was called "As We May Think."
وكان المقال بعنوان "حسبما يمكن أن نعتقد."
And what Vannevar Bush was saying
وما كان يقصده فانيفار بوش
was the way we use information is broken.
هو أن الطريقة التي نستعمل فيها المعلومات هي فاشلة.
We don't work in terms of libraries
نحن لا نعمل مثل المكتبات
and catalog systems and so forth.
ونظم الكاتالوجات وهكذا دواليك.
The brain works by association.
يعمل الدماغ حسب التجميع.
With one item in its thought, it snaps instantly to the next item.
حيث يوجد موضوع واحد في كل فكرة، ثم يمر بسرعة للموضوع التالي.
And the way information is structured
والطريقة التي يتم بها تنظيم المعلومات
is totally incapable of keeping up with this process.
عاجزة تماما عن مواكبة هذه العملية.
And so he suggested a machine,
ولذلك اقترح آلة،
and he called it the memex.
وسماها الميميكس.
And the memex would link information,
والميميكس سيربط المعلومات،
one piece of information to a related piece of information and so forth.
قطعة من المعلومات موصولة بقطعة أخرى من المعلومات وهكذا دواليك.
Now this was in 1945.
كان ذلك في 1945.
A computer in those days
كان الحاسوب في تلك الأيام
was something the secret services used to use for code breaking.
شيئا تستعمله أجهزة المخابرات لفك الشيفرة.
And nobody knew anything about it.
ولم يكن يعلم أحد عنه شيئا.
So this was before the computer was invented.
ولقد كان هذا قبل اختراع الحاسوب.
And he proposed this machine called the memex.
واقترح هذه الآلة التي تدعى الميميكس.
And he had a platform where you linked information to other information,
وكان له منصة تستطيع أن تربط معلومات بمعلومات أخرى.
and then you could call it up at will.
ثم تستطيع أن تستدعي أي معلومة بضغطة زر.
So spinning forward,
و مرورا إلى الأمام،
one of the guys who read this article was a guy called Doug Engelbart,
أحد الأشخاص الذين قرأوا هذا المقال كان يدعى دوغ إنغيلبارت،
and he was a U.S. Air Force officer.
وكان ضابطا في سلاح الجو الأمريكي.
And he was reading it in their library in the Far East.
وكان يقرأه في مكتبة عمله في الشرق الأقصى.
And he was so inspired by this article,
وألهمه المقال كثيرا،
it kind of directed the rest of his life.
لقد وجّهت تلك المقالة نوعا ما بقية حياته.
And by the mid-60s, he was able to put this into action
ومع منتصف الستينات، كان قادرا على ترجمة المقال إلى فعل
when he worked at the Stanford Research Lab in California.
عندما عمل في مختبر ستانفورد للبحث في كاليفورنيا.
He built a system.
لقد أنشأ نظاما.
The system was designed to augment human intelligence, it was called.
صُمم النظام لزيادة الذكاء البشري، حسبما قيل.
And in a premonition of today's world
واستشرافا لعالم اليوم المتعلق
of cloud computing and softwares of service,
بالحوسبة السحابية وبرمجيات الخدمات،
his system was called NLS
سُمي نظامه أن أل أس
for oN-Line System.
اختصارا لعبارة نظم معلومات عبر الخطوط الهاتفية
And this is Doug Engelbart.
وهذا هو دوغ إنغيلبارت.
He was giving a presentation at the Fall Joint Computer Conference
كان يقدم عرضا خلال المؤتمر الخريفي المشترك للحاسوب
in 1968.
في 1968.
What he showed --
ما عرضه حينها --
he sat on a stage like this, and he demonstrated this system.
هو أن جلس على خشبة مسرح مثل هذا، وقام بعرض هذا النظام.
He had his head mic like I've got.
وكان يضع ميكروفون الرأس مثلما أضعه الآن.
And he works this system.
وشغّل النظام.
And you can see, he's working between documents
وكما ترون، فهو يمرّ بين الوثائق
and graphics and so forth.
والغرافيك وهكذا دواليك.
And he's driving it all
وهو يتحكم بكل النظام
with this platform here,
عبر هذه المنصة هنا،
with a five-finger keyboard
التي تحتوي على لوحة مفاتيح تستخدم فيها الأصابع الخمسة
and the world's first computer mouse,
وأول فأرة حاسوب في العالم،
which he specially designed in order to do this system.
صممها خصيصا لتشغيل هذا النظام.
So this is where the mouse came from as well.
ومن هنا أيضا أتت الفأرة
So this is Doug Engelbart.
إذن هذا هو دوغ إنغيلبارت.
The trouble with Doug Engelbart's system
الخلل في نظام دوغ إنغيلبارت
was that the computers in those days cost several million pounds.
كان أن الحواسيب في تلك الأيام كلّفت عدّة ملايين من الجنيهات.
So for a personal computer,
إذن فيما يتعلق للحاسوب الشخصي،
a few million pounds was like having a personal jet plane;
عدة ملايين من الجنيهات كانت تكفي لشراء طائرة نفاثة خاصة؛
it wasn't really very practical.
في الحقيقة لم يكن ذلك عمليا.
But spin on to the 80s
ولكن مرورا إلى الثمانينيات
when personal computers did arrive,
عندما تقدمت فعلا الحواسيب الشخصية،
then there was room for this kind of system on personal computers.
وكان هناك "فسحة تسويقية" للحواسيب الشخصية لهذا النوع من النظام.
And my company, OWL
وشركتي، أو دبليو أل
built a system called Guide for the Apple Macintosh.
أنشأت نظاما سُمي "دليل ماكنتوش آبل".
And we delivered the world's first hypertext system.
ونشرنا أول نظام للنص الفائق في العالم.
And this began to get a head of steam.
و بدأ يحقق انتشارا.
Apple introduced a thing called HyperCard,
طرحت آبل شيئا إسمه هايبر كارد،
and they made a bit of a fuss about it.
وأرفقته بكثير من الأضواء الإعلامية .
They had a 12-page supplement in the Wall Street Journal the day it launched.
كان لديهم يوم إطلاقه ملحق ضم 12 صفحة في وول ستريت جورنال.
The magazines started to cover it.
وبدأت المجلات في تغطيته.
Byte magazine and Communications at the ACM
مجلة بايت ومجلة كوميونيكيشنز أوف ذي أي سي أم
had special issues covering hypertext.
كان لديهم أعداد خاصة غطت النص الفائق.
We developed a PC version of this product
وطورنا نسخة من هذا المنتج للحاسوب الشخصي
as well as the Macintosh version.
علاوة على نسخة للماكنتوش.
And our PC version became quite mature.
وأصبحت نسختنا للحاسوب المحمول ناضجة نوعا ما.
These are some examples of this system in action in the late 80s.
هذه بعض الأمثلة من هذا النظام وهو يعمل في أواخر الثمانينيات.
You were able to deliver documents, were able to do it over networks.
كان بإمكان المستخدمين نشر الوثائق، كانوا قادرين على فعل ذلك عبر الشبكات.
We developed a system such
طورنا نظاما كان لديه
that it had a markup language based on html.
لغة ترميز قائمة على لغة ترميز النص الفائق.
We called it hml: hypertext markup language.
أسميناها لغة ترميز النص الفائق.
And the system was capable of doing
وكان النظام قادرا على القيام
very, very large documentation systems over computer networks.
بأنظمة توثيق كبيرة جدا جدا عبر شبكات الحواسيب.
So I took this system to a trade show in Versailles near Paris
لذلك حملت هذا النظام لمعرض تجارة في فرساي قرب باريس
in late November 1990.
في أواخر نوفمبر 1990.
And I was approached by a nice young man called Tim Berners-Lee
وفاتحني رجل شاب لطيف يدعى تيم بيرنرز- لي قائلا
who said, "Are you Ian Ritchie?" and I said, "Yeah."
"هل أنت إيان ريتشي؟" وقلت"نعــــــــم."
And he said, "I need to talk to you."
وقال "أريد أن أتحدث معك."
And he told me about his proposed system called the World Wide Web.
وأخبرني عن نظامه المقترَح الذي يُدعى الشبكة العنكبتوية العالمية.
And I thought, well, that's got a pretentious name,
وفكرت، حسنا، إن لديه إسما متباهيا،
especially since the whole system ran on his computer in his office.
خاصة عندما اشتغل كل النظام عبر حاسوب في مكتبه.
But he was completely convinced that his World Wide Web
لكنه كان مقتنعا تماما بأن شبكته العنكبوتية العالمية
would take over the world one day.
ستنتشر في العالم يوما ما.
And he tried to persuade me to write the browser for it,
وحاول إقناعي بأن أصمم المتصفح الخاص به،
because his system didn't have any graphics or fonts or layout or anything;
لأنه نظامه لم يكن يحتوي على غرافيك أو خطوط أو تصميم أو أي شيئ
it was just plain text.
كان نصا خالصا فقط.
I thought, well, you know, interesting,
اعتقدت بأن ذلك سيكون ممتعا،
but a guy from CERN, he's not going to do this.
لكن شخصا من المركز الأوروبي للأبحاث النووية لن يقوم بذلك.
So we didn't do it.
وفعلا لم نقم بذلك.
In the next couple of years,
وفي السنتين اللاحقتين،
the hypertext community didn't recognize him either.
لم يعترف به مجتمع النص الفائق أيضا.
In 1992, his paper was rejected for the Hypertext Conference.
في 1992، رُفض عرض ورقته البحثية في مؤتمر النص الفائق.
In 1993,
في 1993،
there was a table at the conference in Seattle,
كان هناك طاولة في نفس المؤتمر في سياتل،
and a guy called Marc Andreessen
وكان هناك شخص يُدعى مارك أندريسن
was demonstrating his little browser for the World Wide Web.
قام بعرض متصفحه الصغير للويب
And I saw it, and I thought, yep, that's it.
ورأيته، واعتقدت أن ذلك المنتج سينجح.
And the very next year, in 1994, we had the conference here in Edinburgh,
وفي السنة الموالية نفسها، في 1994، عقدنا المؤتمر هنا في أدنبره،
and I had no opposition in having Tim Berners-Lee as the keynote speaker.
ولم يكن لي معارضة لوجود تيم بيرنرز-لي متحدثا رئيسيا.
So that puts me in pretty illustrious company.
و وضعني ذلك في خانة زمرة معينة من المشاهير.
There was a guy called Dick Rowe
كان هناك في تلك الزمرة شخص يُدعى ديك راو
who was at Decca Records and turned down The Beatles.
الذي كان يعمل في ديكا ريكوردز وخذل البيتلز.
There was a guy called Gary Kildall
كان هناك شخص يُدعى غاري كيلدول
who went flying his plane
الذي ذهب ليحلق بطائرته
when IBM came looking for an operating system
عندما جاءت آي بي أم لتبحث عن نظام تشغيل
for the IBM PC,
للحاسوب الشخصي من نوع آي بي أم،
and he wasn't there, so they went back to see Bill Gates.
ولم يكن موجودا هناك، لذلك عدلوا عن ذلك وعادوا لرؤية بيل غيتس.
And the 12 publishers
والناشرون الإثنا عشر
who turned down J.K. Rowling's Harry Potter, I guess.
الذين صدّوا مؤلفة هاري بوتر جاي كاي رولينغ، حسبما أعتقد.
On the other hand, there's Marc Andreessen
ومن ناحية أخرى، هناك مارك أندريسن
who wrote the world's first browser for the World Wide Web.
الذي صمم أول متصفح للشبكة العنكبوتية العالمية.
And according to Fortune magazine,
وحسب مجلة فورتشن،
he's worth 700 million dollars.
تبلغ ثروته 700 مليون دولار.
But is he happy?
لكن هل هو سعيد؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)